<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title></title><link href="http://www.rootranger.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.rootranger.com/feeds/tech.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.rootranger.com/</id><updated>2017-12-06T06:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>WordPress on your Machine..made Easy!</title><link href="http://www.rootranger.com/Local%20Dev%20environment...HOORAY!.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-06T06:00:00-05:00</published><author><name>simzilla</name></author><id>tag:www.rootranger.com,2017-12-06:Local Dev environment...HOORAY!.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Soooo...I did it again.  I went months without posting anything.  Why you ask? Because I am a mess of projects...and emotions.  I started writing this super long post about this Python project I created to email myself a daily workout from a plan I created but then I hurt myself and had to scale back my training.  My depression made me abandon this post.  I started jacking with a Raspberry Pi...it had a broken usb port...so I set it aside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My life has been a flurry of abandoned work and unrealized dreams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worst of all, my wife finally decided to relocate her website.  I rushed to get ready to create a new one for her...I took too long so she paid somebody (sadness), but in making the attempt I did some research into setting up a development environment for WordPress on my local machine.  Below I've documented my steps for my many readers...and mostly so that I can remember how to do it myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't my first rodeo.  I have a nasty and abused laptop that I utilize for developing and running scripts.  During my first trip into WordPress development I threw a LAMP stack on it and went for it.  This was a total pain!  I had to SSH into it or VNC and I knew that it would be configured differently from whatever host platform I decided to go with.  It got all full of crap, I couldn't roll anything back, and eventually I just shut it off and forgot about it.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last go around I discovered the many V's of WordPress development.  VV and VVV allow me to create virtual-environments on my laptop so I can mirror the configuration of my host pretty closely and I can do everything without any extra hops to another physical machine.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Varying Variable Vagrants" src="images/post4/VVV.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can run as many sites as I want, delete, edit, or publish them from anywhere and its all pretty easy.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you are going to need the most current version of  &lt;a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/"&gt;VirtualBox&lt;/a&gt;.  There are other virtual machine clients but VirtualBox is free.  I'm sure VMWare or some other viewer will work but if you venture down this road you can pack up your money bags and go alone!  It is super easy to install VirtualBox and there is a ton of support available if you jack something up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, you are going to need &lt;a href="www.vagrantup.com"&gt;Vagrant&lt;/a&gt;.  Vagrant is a tool, for use with your Virtual Machine client, that builds and allows you to manage virtual machine environments. So if you are a developer you can create an isolated and reproducible environment that will mirror the environment you intend your users to utilize.  This is like a building block toward our journey of creating an environment for our WordPress works.  It is really easy to install.  Go to the webpage and download the version that matches your system.  I have only utilized it in the command-line.  I don't even think there is a GUI interface...so load it up and you are good to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have Vagrant installed there are a couple of plug-ins you can install that are supposed to make creating new sites easier.  Personally, I never got either of them to work.  Try this out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;vagrant plugin install vagrant-hostupdater
vagrant plugin install vagrant-triggers
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These plugins are supposed to automatically update your host file and allow you to add new sites with ease.  Like I said, they didn't work for me but updating the host file yourself is as easy as updating a host file...I'll cover it...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Picking up the Vagrants&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So VVV, or Varying Variable Vagrants, is the piece of software that brings this all together.  VVV is an open-source vagrant configuration.  This particular configuration has been designed specifically for use with WordPress.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="VVV on Github" src="images/post4/VVVgithub.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have yet to attempt a deployment from a site I have worked on using VVV, but prototyping, learning, and building out a few sites has really been great using VVV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installation is fairly straight forward.  All you really need to do is clone VVV straight from GitHub to wherever you will be doing your development.  For instance, I have the following folder layout:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Local VVV" src="images/post4/Filestruct.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to get VVV into the desired location navigate to it from the command-line and execute your clone:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git clone git https://github.com/Varying-Vagrant-Vagrants/VVV.git
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can also download the zip, but that is way less l33t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once VVV is in place, and extracted if necessary, all you have to do to run it for the first time is run the following command from with the VVV folder:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;vagrant up
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The first time you run it you might as well turn on some Netflix.  I think it took my system about 45 minutes to setup the VM and download some updates.  Once its all finished, navigate to one of the canned URLs like &lt;a href="vvvtest.dev"&gt;vvvtest&lt;/a&gt; and you should see a test page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Test Page" src="images/post4/vvvtest.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To stop the VM, run the command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;vagrant halt
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Creating a Page of your Own&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point you are all setup. Personally, I ran into a little trouble right about now.  Creating a new site is simple, but if the plug-ins don't all jive you have to jump through some hoops to edit your site.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you have to create the site, enter this command in your VVV directory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;vv create
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You will get hit with a few questions regarding the name of your site and the url you would like to access it from locally, usually something.dev, make sure you remember this url since it is what you will use to access your site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that command is done running you should be given a command prompt.  At this point you need to run the command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;vagrant up --provision
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This will ensure your new sites are accessible and ready for work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Did it work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me start by apologizing...I'm about to save you hours of development frustration...the right of passage that we all love.  If you are like me, you will see that your VM is running and try to navigate to your newly created site.  Maybe your plug-ins will all be chugging along and you'll land on this site and start WordPressing it up.  I however, did not have this experience.  My VM was running but I could not navigate to any newly created sites.  The issue here, I found after several hours, was my host file but there is a really easy fix.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are going to have to find the file "vvv-config.yml" in your VVV folder.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="VVV Directory" src="images/post4/vvv-configpic.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This file contains a bunch of configurations for your VVV environment, and if your junk is not working, it most likely does not contain an entry for your newly created site.  If thats the case, you will have to create a really simple entry, that will in turn ensure your host file is edited to reflect the new site.  It should look like the example below (where bpwb.dev is the new site I tried to create):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Edited vvv-config file" src="images/post4/vvv-configpic2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you have made these changes run another:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;vagrant up --provision
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After your VM is done spinning up you should be able to access your new site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who knows what's next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a ton of little projects that I am trying to sort out.  I have a lot of good ideas and its really daunting.  So much...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I talked about my Python workout script...that was pretty depressing...I plan on writing about it but I think I'll do it as a short blurb and a share of some code from GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, my priorities right now are building a Wordpress site for a side project I am doing with my wife, re-doing my static site, creating a wireless hotspot for my VPN at home, and rebuilding a stainless steel road bike I picked up for a few bucks.  Very unfocused stuff.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have some free time over the next few weeks so hopefully I will be able to rapid fire out a few posts.  I'll probably even throw something up about the bike to save it for posterity since nobody reads this thing anyways.  Don't hold your breath.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="fun"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="learning"></category></entry><entry><title>Lessons Learned: Pelican</title><link href="http://www.rootranger.com/Lessons%20Learned%20after%20playing%20with%20Pelican.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-31T06:00:00-04:00</published><author><name>simzilla</name></author><id>tag:www.rootranger.com,2017-07-31:Lessons Learned after playing with Pelican.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been a bad blogger...a terrible blogger.  The thing I feared most happened to me.   It has been many moons since my last post.  I have had a lot going on and I have gazed into my screen, read pages of code, wanted to write...then I shut my screen in frustration and went on to something else.  A lot has changed in this time...the political climate, the actual climate, technology, my willingness to try and turn something designed to be bare bones into something flashy...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus we are here!  Lessons learned from a few months using Pelican and my first endeavor into the web.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lesson 1: There is not a very active Pelican community&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know whats boring? Reading a ton of documentation on GitHub and cross-referencing a bunch of code with some html templates to try and figure out how a static-page generator works.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="How does it work!!" src="images/post3/figuring.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the past few months I've done a significant amount of reading about various static site generators.  There are some that seem lively and inviting, like a nice over priced middle-class community and then there is Pelican. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican's community is pretty non-existent.  It would be nice to jump onto a sub-reddit dedicated to Pelican development or find answers to all of my questions on Stack Overflow but my success utilizing both of these resources has been limited.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there are a couple of reasons for this.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the web development community in general is not focused on static site development.  APIs and more complex sites open the door to a great deal of conversation whereas, with a static site, a generator is a convenience rather than a necessity.  If I wanted to I could write my whole site in html...Pelican just streamlines the process. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, simplicity.  Its not really that complicated to do stuff with a static site.  Its basically html and some sort of templating engine.  As I was diving into my site I noticed I was not getting accurate Google Analytics results.  It was really easy for me to trouble shoot by pasting the requisite Google provisioned javascript into different places within the html that Pelican generated and see what worked.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could easily solve all of my problems this way.  What I really want to do is add a neat little picture to my feed list.  Something eye-catching for all of my fans to click on instead of words that they have to waste time reading.  I could hard-code this and make it laborious on myself but then why use a generator.  I want to take advantage of what its already doing...but first I have to figure out exactly what it is doing.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since trouble shooting is so easy, I guess most people don't require a ton of help as they develop, but Pelican is for people focused on getting words out...not really on presenting content to the general public.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lesson 2: Where's the Documentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate the documentation available for &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.4.0/index.html"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe it's just me and the way I like content laid out but I cannot stand it.  I've messed with my site, I have set out with goals in term's of changes, and I have spent way to long staring at the documentation.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think I have referenced the documentation successfully a single time.  I made several attempts but I just don't find the information provided adequate.  Maybe it's me and I just do not have the patience for crawling through the documentation to solve a specific problem. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel like it is just outdated.  Nobody really presents to the general public using Pelican so there is no reason to keep up with trends.  The user base is pretty knowledgeable and I feel like people with specific needs tend to create there own generators as opposed to refining these old ones.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure thats something I really want to get into.  There are a million static blog flavors out there and I don't want to be a part of the over-population epidemic plaguing our world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lesson 3: Pelican almost killed my blog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been messing around with the theme I chose out of the bucket that comes packaged with Python.  Months worth of messing around! I couldn't take it anymore...I had to go away...get to my happy place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Get AWAY!!!" src="images/post3/bigsur.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making pictures and watching it come to life was fun at first.  It was new and I was cautious...probably more than I needed to be.  After that, it was tedious to make changes, streamlined changes anyway.  I could hack my way through stuff, but I just am not a fan of the way I am able to make things look.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never produced anything in Pelican, or saw something on the web made in Pelican, that I thought was instantly appealing.  Nothing flashy or inviting and thats kind of what I was hoping for.  The attempts and tries turned to tedium, the tedium turned to stagnate RootRanger web content and now DIVORCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;In The Works&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So effective immediately, a new look for RootRanger is in the works.  Im going to stick with a static blog but instead of jumping into the first thing that tickles my fancy I am going to be a little more deliberate in what I decide to work with.  Expect to read about this process in my next few blogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to this, I recently picked up a Raspberry Pi 3 to mess around with.  For a while I have been working on a project meant to streamline my fitness exploits.  I've been getting soft and it is time to whip myself back into shape.  I wrote a little program that emails me my daily workout schedule every morning.  It is fed by a CSV file with my master plan and it scrapes a few web pages when necessary.  I plan on adding a web side to control it...hopefully remotely.  I'm going to write about this in the future too...it's a little off topic but fun.  Give me a little time to make it super sweet and, to workup a mental sweat as they say, and then check back in.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="fun"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="learning"></category></entry><entry><title>Time for an ENDORSEMENT!</title><link href="http://www.rootranger.com/deciding%20to%20start%20with%20static.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-08T06:00:00-04:00</published><author><name>simzilla</name></author><id>tag:www.rootranger.com,2016-10-08:deciding to start with static.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The most controversial decision of our time is upon us.  Something that I know every man and woman cares immensely about...  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What platform should I use for my blog?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously though, perhaps this decision is slightly less divisive than say a presidential election, but personally, I have had an internal debate raging over the past few months.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one side, you have the content management system (CMS)/database based blog.  In my opinion, the only candidate seeking to make the internet great again in this neighborhood is Wordpress.  The competition, competing for my heart and mind, is the static site created using a generator or some form or fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Framing my Problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point I feel like its helpful for me to reframe my problem.  The whole point of this search is to end up with a site capable of supporting my wife's business which needs to display her portfolio, direct traffic to her services, and support her frequent blogging.  It's possible that she may someday delve into e-commerce but right now it is not a priority.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel it is also important for me to consider the computer literacy of the user.  My wife is fairly technically savvy...she has actually taught me a lot about managing search engine optimization (SEO) but she does not like getting in the weeds as far as the framework or platform goes.  She rarely uses the command line to run tools but I think I could provide her a few guides and throw a few scripts together that would make command line stuff easy for her.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, making this assessment is vital.  I've been in several situations where I was forced to manage a website simply because I was a "computer person" and nobody else knew how to manage a fancy site that some developer setup, published, and abandoned.  The complexity of the site meant that it was doomed to rot and die a useless death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, my wife did a little digging around prior to me beginning this journey.  She talked to a few web-developer type people and I was really surprised by their offerings.  Perhaps it was because she was in such a preliminary stage of planning, but it seemed that most were ready to throw a canned Wordpress site together, send her a big invoice, and call it a day.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to give the user, my wife in this case, something that she can manage without my help 98% of the time, but I want to do this while making sure the product fits her needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Back to the options&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the sake of completeness, I'll mention Wix-type canned platforms for creating a site.  This is what my wife is currently using for her site and it falls short of what she needs.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Setareh Beauty brought to you by Wix" src="images/post_2/setarehB_wix.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general these platforms offer very limited control.  It is my personal opinion that the ability to dive into a platform and manipulate it free of constraints is really valuable.  For instance, my wife has had some issues getting organic traffic to her site.  A search for make-up artist in city X does not readily return her site.  This can be rectified by facilitating proper search engine indexing and then performing some search engine optimization.  Wix indexes their sites in a standard manner and it seems that, though some revision has taken place, many search engines still don't like it.  Optimizing from this point is kind of a futile effort, it is possible but it involves plug-ins and, in some cases, money.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wordpress&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a man who appreciates solid data.  That being said I can tell you this...there are a ton of Wordpress sites smattered around the internet (&amp;lt;--that is not solid data).  I wanted to throw some number at you with a source, but deploying websites on your platform is kind of a business so I've found it about as difficult to find solid deployment info as it is to find Presidential candidate tax information.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe look here if you want some unreliable data: &lt;a href="http://trends.builtwith.com/cms"&gt;http://trends.builtwith.com/cms &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Picture via trends.builtwith.com/cms" src="/images/post_2/usage.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want my honest opinion, I think that Wordpress is probably where we will end up.  It is really envogue it seems, people like seeing alot of the same thing, and the photography/make-up/beauty industry is consumed with it.  I am hesitant to jump in this direction to quickly though.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A CMS, like Wordpress, utilizes a database to store content.  When a visitor accesses content over the web the database is accessed and the requested content is loaded.  The database access and subsequent load times don't matter too much when one or two visitors are pulling content every hour or if link speed is not an issue , but it is hard to scale.  There are means of pushing content to distribution networks but this is certainly not trivial. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wordpress can be great if it is setup soundly and effectively, periodically maintained, and populated by an individual who does not want to dive into the weeds every time they add content.  Though that fits the needs of my user/wife to some extent, it isn't very appetizing to me as I like getting in the weeds and getting everything customized and optimal.  Dynamically accessing a database is great if you need it (web apps, rapidly updating content, real-time functions) but I think it creates a lot of moving parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Wordpress Logo" src="/images/post_2/wordpress.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a photography blog for example.  I'm sitting in a coffee shop and just pulled one up and I can tell it was created, and is managed, using a CMS.  This individual's blog was last updated almost a year ago (not rapidly updating content) and other than that its just a bunch of static pictures (no scrolling content, no widgets, nothing special).  There are probably a handful of database requests and then loading periods that need to take place before I see a picture and I have to sit here and wait for it...this happens every time I click on something.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I worry about is security.  I feel like, from my wondering about the internet, people don't worry about security on their blogs (and even some small business sites).  There is a good on-line &lt;a href="https://wordpress.org/about/security/"&gt;white paper&lt;/a&gt; that addresses several security topics with respect to Wordpress.  What I take away from all of this is that you can't take security for granted on your blog...especially if you want to get into e-commerce.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll re-address this topic in a subsequent blog, but for now we will move on.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Static Blogs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first began my computer exploits I created a website that I wrote in html.  It had some words and a few pictures...all in a straight column down the screen, it was pretty awesome.  Now it seems that pages adhering to a similar concept are making a comeback. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A static blog framework utilizes templates, css, and a post to create a static html web page.  This page can then be placed on a server with the pictures and other content required to display it properly.  It doesn't get rendered dynamically, there are no databases, and it's size is relatively small.  Additionally, these frameworks typically facilitate a great deal of customization.  The themes are fairly simple, there are still plug-ins for performing many tasks, and serving this content is really easy and low cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far a security goes, there really aren't any moving parts.  I'm not going to say its 100% secure (you're host could get hacked, you might be using a weak password), but the attack surface of your base site is reduced. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the downside, we are talking about some increased complexity over a longer time period.  With Wordpress, the complexity is all up-front really, besides maintenance.  With a static blog everything is a little more complex.  Every new post requires that the site be re-rendered and all the changed files need to be updated.  A service like Git-hub, that can help automate change control, is vital to the static blog.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are numerous static blog frameworks.  Take your programming language of choice and hit up Google.  I currently prefer Python.  This website is all rendered using &lt;a href="http://blog.getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;.  There is an online community for seeking Pelican support, but what I have found is that it is somewhat outdated or neglected.  Many tech type blogs...like this one I guess...are written using a static blog.  I think this contributes to the lack of updated information.  When you get Pelican you pretty much get everything you need to develop away.  The template files are fairly easy to manipulate as are the configuration files.  I chose a theme and then messed with it to the point that its almost unrecognizable when compared to the original.  I think that is pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="www.github.com"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; provides a service Github Pages that allows you to host small sites like these for free.  Check it out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My Choice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have obviously made the choice to delve into the static blog first.  I feel like it is a good place to learn a little bit about blogging and web presentation intricacies.  Just with these two posts I have learned a great deal about serving web content, analyzing traffic with Google Analytic tools, and procrastinating.  There are several guides out on the web that can lead you through getting a site like mine up.  To be honest, I found that they were all flawed in some way...either outdated or erroneous, but as an aggregate they helped me get this site up.  In my next post I am going to go over some lessons learned and the stuff I feel like you need to know to have a static blog of your own.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="fun"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="learning"></category></entry><entry><title>What am I looking for?</title><link href="http://www.rootranger.com/rootranger%20purpose.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-14T17:53:00-04:00</published><author><name>simzilla</name></author><id>tag:www.rootranger.com,2016-07-14:rootranger purpose.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Professionally speaking, the last few years have been a wild ride.  I suppose I haven’t been professional for very long, so maybe wild is all I know!  I went from a Computer Science undergrad degree to a job that was supposed to be technical but wasn’t really fulfilling at all to a job that was not technical at all but was very challenging and awesome, both physically and mentally, but not related in any way to computers.  I worked in this field for 8-ish years and really loved it but couldn't turn down the opportunity to pursue my graduate degree in Computer Science.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst pursuing my undergraduate degree, I convinced myself that I hated computers.  Following college, for the better part of ten years, I had little concern for the pursuit of computer science related things.  I'm not sure what changed, I probably developed a little discipline somewhere along the way, but I found that I was really interested in this field while getting my graduate degree.  It turned from something I was doing purely because of opportunity to something that I really enjoy learning about.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My recent academic focus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been in school for a long time, way too long.   Recently I have been doing a lot of work in networking in a practical and theoretical sense.  I’ve been working on a really practically based radio project for the last year.  I’m going to write about it later on because it has given me the opportunity to do some really cool Python programming.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to write about a ton of academic or professional stuff here though.  I intend for this blog to be fun and simple.  Maybe I'll throw the random interesting tidbit in here every once in a while. BUT I by no means intend for this to be my primary focus....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I do want to take away from academia is the content format of this blog.  I was recently listening to a podcast I like, &lt;a href="https://talkpython.fm"&gt;"Talk Python to Me"&lt;/a&gt;, and the guest made some interesting comments.  It was all pretty intense, but his basic thought was that a technical type blog ought to be more like a white paper and less like the reporting of the recent celebrity happening.  Rather than being super frequent, I am going to try and be more well thought out, structured and approachable for the layman.  Which brings me to…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ranging? and Why We Are All Here...&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to produce something cool.  I want to produce a lot of things at a rapid pace.  Maybe that’s what bothered me the most about my undergrad experience.  Don’t get me wrong, I loved it...how could I not? I was a student at the finest educational institution in all the land. However, when I finished my degree I didn’t feel like I could create anything or do anything really useful (that's definitely my fault by the way).  But now that I enjoy this stuff I feel like I've really had my head up in the theory clouds and I don’t find that super enjoyable either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wife began blogging in support of her small business endeavors and my eyes were opened to all of these awesome platforms on the web and how interesting it all was.  I think web production is a really interesting collision of technical and artistic pursuits.  There are so many platforms, capabilities, and ways to express one's self.   Diving in is overwhelming! I have a pretty solid background in this stuff and I get overwhelmed.  I feel that every single time I jump into a platform intending to learn it, I find something I like better and want to learn.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In colonial times, small units of men set about the wilderness to observe the untamed areas around settlements.  These men "ranged" these areas to gain information and relay it back to the larger settlements for their benefit.  For me, the web is my untamed, unknown and ever-changing frontier.  I intend to wonder around, semi-aimlessly, gathering information and relaying it in a digestible manner right HERE!  The goal is to try out some platforms and write about them in a simple way.  I want to talk about their practicality, usefulness, security, and approachability and make this information understandable to a wide audience.  I doubt there are many people out there who find this stuff as interesting as I do, but maybe you are thinking about starting a blog for your small business or project and something I do here can help you choose a direction.  I think that’d be pretty awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Near-Term Plans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it’s a little hard to tell but I have kind of been working on this particular site for a little while.  Not too long, I get distracted easily, but its tough to be ready to throw something out to the world (even when you don’t have high hopes for its mass consumption).  Eventually I had to decide to not let perfect be the enemy of good enough.  So here it is Version 1 of this blog made using a platform called Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next post is going to talk about this process, how I set it up, and why I chose a static site generator.  Wordpress is a really popular platform right now, and I think its pretty cool, but is it perfect for everybody?  I am not sure that it is.  My next blog is going to talk about why I think this is the case and I am going to go over how simple it was to use Pelican to make a blog. Just a side note, I’m really big on using open source software, I think a lot of people will find the solutions I propose easy on the pocket book and pretty awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that I really want to post about the project I am working on with White Space radios.  That one is a little bit of a deviation from the web focus, but not really.  Its just a little lower level.  Really though it’s the future.  The spectrum we utilize to communicate is becoming crowded and White Space products seek to alleviate some of that congestion.  If you live in a populated area and have trouble with your Wi-Fi connection you are already suffering from this problem. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all of that things are only going to get wilder!  I intend on constantly shaking up the look and functionality of this blog as I explore new things.  I feel like this current incantation is super simple so I have a lot of room to explore.  It’s a big world out there…lots of room for RootRanging!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="fun"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="learning"></category></entry></feed>